International Workers Order (IWO) Records 5276
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Workers Order (IWO) Records
1915-2002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5276
42.44 cubic feet
42.4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists of the records of the International Workers' Order (IWO). Papers include many items related to Socialist, Communist and radical activities.
3338460
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 30, 1986
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, March 10, 2022
Biographical / Historical
The International Workers Order (IWO) was an insurance, mutual benefit and fraternal organization founded in 1930 and disbanded in 1954 as the result of legal action undertaken by the state of New York in 1951 on the grounds that the organization was too closely linked to the Communist Party. At its height in the years immediately following World War II, the IWO reached nearly 200,000 members and provided low-cost health and life insurance, medical and dental clinics, and supported foreign-language newspapers, cultural and educational activities. The organization also operated a summer camp and cemeteries for its members.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5276: International Workers Order (IWO) Records 5940: International Workers Order Case Files 5940 mf: International Workers Order's Immigration and Naturalization Files on Microfilm
Socialism -- United States; Communism -- United States; Bedacht, Max, 1883-1972; Greene, David; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Milgram, Sam; Pezner, Sam; Saltzman, Reuben; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Thompson, Louise; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981; American Committee for Yugoslav Relief; American Committee of Jewish Writers, Artists and Scientists; American Jewish Assembly; American Jewish Congress; American Jewish Labor Council; B'nai B'rith; Distributive, Processing, and Office Workers of America; German-American Committee on Spanish Relief; Hebrew Sheltering of Immigrant Aid Society of America; Hellenic American Society; Illinois. Department of Insurance; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; International Workers Order; National Conference of Christians and Jews; National Urban League; New York (State). Insurance Department; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee on Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies and Organizations; Pennsylvania. Insurance Department; Russian Mutual Aid Society; United Office and Professional Workers of America.; Yiddish Cooperative Book League
3338460
- Pre IWO Documents, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Workingmen's Sick, Benevolent & Educational Federation. Includes correspondence & Certificate of Incorporation. Joseph Kertesz, Executive Secretary correspondence with legal representatives re laws of various states relative to fraternal beneficiary soc.
- Pre IWO Documents, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Workingmen's Sick, Benevolent & Educational Federation. Includes correspondence & Certificate of Incorporation. Joseph Kertesz, Executive Secretary correspondence with legal representatives re laws of various states relative to fraternal beneficiary soc
- Pre IWO Documents, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Constitutions - IWO, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Included in "minutes" are actual minutes, summaries of minutes & reports.
- Minutes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Minutes of Plenary Sessions of the General Executive Board of the International Workers Order, Inc., 1938; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Held at Hotel Center, New York City, September 10th and llth, 1938. 25 pages.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1938; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    9/10/38 - General Secretary Max Bedacht reported to the Board on the convention goal of 300, 000 members by next convention (2 years). Suggests more rapid growth & development of IWO, discusses weaknesses & shortcomings and the importance to organize politically not mechanically. "We must mobilize anti-fascist fighters -- not membership solicitors". Discusses how to organize lodges, educating the public to the meaning of proletarian fraternalism, improving communication between national & local leadership. Bedacht then submitted a plan for the general membership drive.
  - Item 3: Report by National Treasure Peter Shipka, 1938; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    9/11/38 - National Treasurer, Peter Shipka - submitted financial report, discussed membership in relation to dues income, and selling sanitorium stamps.
  - Item 4: Report by English Section Secretary Louise Thompson, 1938; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    English Section Secretary - Louise Thompson - read letter of President Weiner from Commissioner of In- surance, Commonwealth of Massachusetts which states that IWO is communist. Thompson comments that Massachusetts Commission created its own Dies Committee to engage in a "Red" hunt. Explains steps taken when the letter arrived & what occurred at the following hearings.
- Minutes, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Minutes of the Semi-Annual Plenary Session of the General Executive Board of the International Workers Order, Inc., 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Held at Manhattan Center, New York City, March 4th, 5th and 6th, 1939. 27 pages.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3/4/39 - General Secretary Max Bedacht's report - possibility of establishing a home for aged members, status of the campaign for doubling membership by the next convention, inadequate sick benefit fund, dealing with neighborhood problems as a means to increasing membership. He states that growth in English speaking lodges is a priority and discusses organizers will be help responsible for speeding up growth in their areas, leadership training in May.
  - Item 3: Report by General Counsel J. Brodsky, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    General Counsel J. Brodsky - reports that the Massachusetts Supreme Court decision on license renewal should be handed down any day and that "the outlook is that the decision will be favorable to the Order".
  - Item 4: Report by National Treasure Peter Shipka, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3/5/39 - Treasurer Shipka - submitted financial report as of 12/31/38.
  - Item 5: Report by B. McLaurin, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    B. McLaurin reported favorably for the Auditing.
  - Item 6: Report by N. Polak, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3/6/39 - N. Polak - reports of misappropriation of lodge moneys by financial secretaries and suggests bonding of same.
  - Item 7: Resolutions, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    M. Bedacht - submits resolutions for consideration - including resolutions on work among and with National Groups, and establishment of Negro Work Commission - all passed unanimously.
  - Item 8: Proposals submitted by Brother Levin, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3/6/39 (cont.) - Brother Levin - submitted proposals on educational work - unanimously adopted.
  - Item 9: Minutes of Plenary Session, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    G.E.B. Plenary Session, Summary of Discussion - March 6, 1939. Brother Bedacht. 8 pages.
  - Item 10: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1/4/39 - Report of Max Bedacht, General Secretary I.W.O. To the Organization Committee and Eastern District Organizers Hotel. Pennsylvania, New York. January 4, 1939. 18 pages.
  - Item 11: Various Discussions, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Discusses speeding up the organization effort, campaign quotas, restructuring the apparatus of I.W.O., Figures and comparisons of recruits and losses, analyzes the weakness of English section, suggests consolidation of lodges, role of district leaders as problem solvers in their territory, solutions for turnover, financial problems.
- Minutes, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Summary of Discussions, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Summary of the Discussion By General Secretary Max Bedacht - Meeting of the General Executive Board - January 29, 1940. 5 pages.
  - Item 2: Commendation of Polish Section, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Commended Polish section for successful organizing, mentioned turnover discussion including Philadelphia, Jewish, Italian, English, Chicago, Ukrainian lodges. Political Responsibilities of Districts, citing Turkish lodge problems.
  - Item 3: Minutes of General Executive Board Meeting, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    September 14-15-16, 1940. Hotel Picadilly, New York. 4 pages.
  - Item 4: Report by Herbert Benjamin, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Brother Benjamin submitted report on Social Security Campaign, during discussion, proposals made including endorsement of American Youth Act, support of bill protecting foreign born - report & proposals adopted. Motions adopted include - American Peace Mobilization, constitutional changes.
- Minutes, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    April 11, 1941. 1 page.
  - Item 2: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    September 3, 1941. 1 page. Routine.
  - Item 3: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    October 21, 1941. 6 pages. Resolution passed supporting Federal Program for Civilian Defense including directives for participation in civilian defense work.
  - Item 4: Minutes of the Plenary Session, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Minutes of Plenary Session of the General Executive Board, February 22-23-24, 1941. 5 pages.
  - Item 5: Guests Introduced, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Two guests introduced - Paul Robeson, Earl Robinson. Discussion of Supreme Courts dismissal of the appeals of William Weiner and Earl Browder. Rev. B.W. Harris of Norfolk addressed the Board, and discussion followed on Negro problems.
  - Item 6: Minutes of the Semi-Annual Plenary Session of the General Executive Board of the International Workers Order, Inc., 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    September 6-7, 1941. 6 pages.
  - Item 7: Resolution to support the U.S. fight against Nazism, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Resolution to support the U.S. fight against Nazism following Hitler's assault on the Soviet Union discussed, support of Earl Browder, William Weiner and Brother Sam Darcy discussed. Resolution opposing discrimination against Negro people in the armed forces & defense industries, and repeal of Poll tax adopted. Resolution selling Oakridge Jewish Cemetery, Proviso Township, Hook County, Illinois lost to IWO Cemetery Dept.
  - Item 8: Summary of Discussions, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Summary of Discussion by Brother Max Bedacht, Meeting of the General Executive Board. September 7, 1941. 3 pages. Includes comments on ending the IWO's isolationism.
- Minutes, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Minutes of the General Executive Board Plenary Sessions, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    February 7-8, 1942. New York City. 10 pages & resolutions.
  - Item 2: Resolution passed enacting a Plan and Program for National Group Victory Councils, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Sam Pevzner read a message from President Weiner. Peter Shipka submitted financial report. Resolutions to urge the House of Representatives to disband the Dies Committee, establish of Victory Councils, to release Earl Browder, to restore Dale Zysman to active duty on the Navy, on Negro rights, citizenship cases were adopted. Resolution to communicate with Secretary of Navy Knox re dismissal of IWO members from Navy Yards in New England on the basis of their IWO membership was referred to Resident Board for Study.
  - Item 3: Speech of Herbert Benjamin, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    General Executive Meeting, February 7, 1942. 11 pages. Discusses how IWO members can best serve the war effort, Victory Councils, Nationality Group, Civil Defense, condemns Red Cross attitude toward Negro donors, Navy attitudes toward Negroes, Browder imprisonment.
  - Item 4: Minutes of General Executive Board, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    June 27, 1942. 6 pages. Discuss resolutions including Herbert Benjamin's resignation, activating more members for the war effort, setting up a Western front, urging Front Line Fighters Fund to intensify Russian War Relief.
  - Item 5: Proceedings of the General Executive Board, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    November 6,7,9, 1942. 7 pages. Senator Stanley Nowak of Michigan addressed the Board. Reaffirmed effort to free William Weiner, read telegram to be sent to CIO convention, discussed membership lethargy re war activities, establishment of a commission to study Negro problems.
- Minutes, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Proceedings of General Executive Board, February 26-27, 1943. 21 pages. Vice President Rockwell Kent in his address to the Board discusses IWO leaders in the armed forces, reads a letter from Dave Green which includes treatment of Negroes in the service
- Minutes, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: Minutes of General Executive Board, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Plenary Session, February 12-13, 1944. 19 pages.
  - Item 2: Milgrom's resolutions call for National Unity, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Milgrom's resolutions call for National Unity citing the Teheran Conference, IWO's role in the war effort, building the Negro American section, Executive Secretary of New York District, Middleton submitted sub report on the general lodges. Brother Vail, Secretary New England District, suggested a name change for I.W.O. Vrabel remarked on the progress of the Slovak Workers Society as affected by the war. Middleton spoke on a fourth term for President Roosevelt, June Gordon reported on the Front Line Fighters Fund, and called on the GEB to take a stand against the "Equal Rights Amendment" which would "wipe out all protective legislation for women..". Rymer proposed a resolution in favor of the Wagner-Murray-Dingell Social Security Bill. A resolution on Legislative work was proposed including passage of Lucas-Green-Worley Federal Ballot Bill, Marcantonio Anti-Poll Tax Bill, Lynch Bill, Marcantonio-Scanlon-Dawson Bills to establish Fair Employment Practice Committee (FEPC), and defeat of Bankhead Bill. Resolutions submitted to combat anti-semitism, on British White Paper re Jewish Community in Palestine, on Japanese slayings of American P.O.W.'s, on deportation of Mrs. E. Browder, on repatriation of Italian anti-fascist refugees to return to Italy, convention arrangements.
  - Item 3: Minutes of General Council Meeting, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 11)
    November 24-25-26, 1944. 15 pages. General Secretary submitted report on plans for the future. Treasurer Shipka discussed new membership certificate decided on at 6th convention, detailing new endowment plan for adults and savings-insurance plan for juniors. Discussion on General Secretary's report included problems of returning veterans. President Croatian Society IWO, Gerlach introduced Mr. Alatko Balokovic who addressed the Council re heroism in Yugoslavia and support of a Relief Ship to Yugoslavia. Discussion on organizing the Negro Community, including repealing the Poll tax, establishing closer relations with organizations of the Negro people. Mr. James W. Ford, 1936 candidate for Vice President was presented and spoke on Negro situation. Mrs. Eurah Gerrard spoke about Negro community in Chicago. Nationality leaders gave reports on their sections. J. Brodsky, IWO attorney read New York Insurance Examiners Report of June 9, 1944 and a motion was made to carry out recommendations contained in that report. Resolution on Social Security, anti-fascist election campaign, anti-discrimination legislation, war risk clause, war relief, servicemen's welfare, anti-semitism, Taylor Rape case.
  - Item 4: Closing Remarks of General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 11)
    General Council Semi-Annual Session, November 24-26, 1944. 4 pages. Stresses cultural activities, political activities.
- Minutes, 1946 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Minutes of General Council Meeting, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 1)
    March 16-17, 1946. 8 pages.
  - Item 2: Message from Rockwell Kent, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 1)
    Message from Rockwell Kent read re cultural activities. Reports from lodges, General Treasurers financial report submitted by Peter Shipka, J. Brodsky reported that Indiana approved license, Wisconsin is still pending and Missouri has denied the application. Resolutions on Social Security, Negro rights, People's Peace Movement, Women's Activities, Price Control, Democratic Europe including condemnation of Churchill's anti- Soviet activities and restoration of Roosevelt's foreign policies.
- Minutes, 1947 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Minutes of General Council Meeting, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    March 1 and 2, 1947. 7 pages.
  - Item 2: Sam Milgrom's Executive Committee Report, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    Included discrimination against national groups by reaction forces, reorientation of General Lodges. Lodge reports, Skipka submitted Treasurer's Report. Letter from Max Bedacht asking for leave of absence and granting of request with full pay. Constitution Committee Report.
  - Item 3: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    December 5, 1947. l page. Discussion on Attorney- General Clark's charges.
  - Item 4: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    December 8, 1947. 3 pages. Statement on Attorney- General Clark's designation of the IWO as an organization of questionable loyalty and discussion on this subject.
  - Item 5: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    December 16, 1947. 1 page.
  - Item 6: Report of Brother Charles Musil, 1947; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 2)
    Report of Brother Charles Musil, to the Executive Committee. 1 page. Establishment Czech Workers Society IWO, report of the Czeck lodges of IWO.
- Minutes, 1948 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Minutes of General Council Meeting, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    Saturday-Sunday, March 13-14, 1948, Fraternal Clubhouse, New York City (10 pages, 10 pages resolutions).
  - Item 2: Report by National Treasure Peter Shipka, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    Secretary-Treasurer, Shipka presented financial report, discussion on new name for the IWO, Memorial observance for J. Brodsky, Welfare Fund, Dave Greene reported on membership drive, Resolutions discussed included adopting an official ritual establishing Welfare Fund, Resolution on unconstitutional list of attorney General Clark, Peace, Work in Negro community, Mrs. Rosa Lee Ingram, Deportation, children's work, English speaking work.
  - Item 3: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    March 8, 1948. 2 pages. Financial Report, proposed name changes for the IWO, discussed aged members in re Welfare Fund, retiring Lee Pressman as attorney for case against Clark listing.
  - Item 4: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    March 30, 1948. 3 pages. Discussed Pilgrimage to Washington arranged by the United Committee to Save the Jewish State and United Nations, General Council meeting re IWO Defense Fund.
  - Item 5: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    April 6, 1948. 2 pages. Discussed name change for IWO, Welfare Fund, IWO Defense, progress of membership drive.
  - Item 6: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    April 7, 1948. 3 pages & 2 page attachment. Discussed cultural festivals, membership drive, letter from Dave Green to organizers.
  - Item 7: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    April 20, 1948. 3 pages. Approved recommendation opposing Un-American Committee Bill in Congress. Discussed State of Pennsylvania's inquiry to Attorney General Clark's listing of IWO, and challenging revocation of IWO's tax exempt status by U.S. Tax Commissioner, radio censorship of foreign language broadcasts.
  - Item 8: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    May 4, 1948. 3 pages. Discussed possibility of organizing Mexican-Americans, Draftee rates, Saltzman reported on his European trip, Negro communities, Defense Fund, defeat of Mundt Bill, and Hobbs Concentration Camp Bill.
  - Item 9: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    June 4, 1948. 3 pages. Discussed Treasury Department's revocation of IWO's tax exempt status.
  - Item 10: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    June 15, 1948. 2 pages. Greene reported on Defense Fund, membership drive. Discussed citizenship cases.
  - Item 11: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    June 29, 1948. 3 pages. Saltzman reported not to recruit Mexican Americans. Recommendation to continue to correspond with the Hollywood Ten. Discussed Platform Hearings of the New Party.
  - Item 12: Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1948; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 3)
    September 14, 1948. 4 pages. Discussed Attorney Clark's reply to court case, Starr reported on delegation to State Department, discussed United Nations week, Shipka reported on Festivals, Greene reported on Defense Fund.
- Reports, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1937; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    To the Enlarged Meeting of the National Executive Committee, I.W.O. - Hotel Latham, New York City, October 2, 1937. 47 pages.
  - Item 2: Membership Discussions, 1937; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Discusses membership - capacity to recruit, maintain members, "We want the masses, we must have them", definition of solidarity and workers fraternal benefit society, changing fascist workers into progressive ones, occupational health, negro problems, women's activities, sports, "anti-fascist month", establishing an official organization.
- Reports, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Report to the G.E.B. by the General Secretary. 21 pages. See: Box 1 - FF 5 - Minutes, 1938 for report summary, also includes list of officers, G.E.B. members, plan for official organ, "Policy To Guide the Order."
- Reports, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 3)
    March 4, 1939, by the General Secretary. 36 pages. See: Box 1 - FF 6 - Minutes, 1939 for report summary.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1939; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 3)
    To The Plenary Session of The General Executive Board, August 26, 1939. 31 pages. Discusses the organizing campaign, home for the aged, structure of I.W.O., Organization of lodges, social membership, English-speaking lodges, support of New Deal, Social Security finances, - also includes pre-convention discussion, "Our Tasks.".
- Reports, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    To the Plenary Session of the G.E.B. - January 27, 1940. 25 pages. Discusses organizing campaign, progress of lodges, consolidation of IWO, attacks on IWO.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)